There is circadian rhythms
that you perform the best in,
and it tends to be your local time,
tends to be your afternoon.
And so if you're traveling
and you're changing time
zones, this matters.
But if you're also manipulating
when you're performing,
even within your time zone,
it can mimic the same effect.
So what I'm getting at here is,
if you can optimize timing,
you can get the benefits
of sleep extension
and improving sleep quality
without changing either of them.
And what I mean by this is,
the research is so cool here
because it comes directly from games won.
There's a lot of research
across a bunch of different sports,
the NBA, the NFL, Major
League Baseball, the NHL.
There's a bunch of studies going back
through 10 years, 30 years,
up to 40 years of historical games.
And they look at these
things and they say,
"Okay, can we predict who's
going to win more games
"based simply on a combination of,
"are they playing in their
right circadian time or not?"
So the example here would be,
let's imagine you have a West Coast team
and they are normally used to competing
at 4:00 pm on the West Coast.
And they travel to the
Midwest or the East Coast,
but they compete at a time
that is still 4:00 on the West Coast time.
So it's their normal circadian rhythm.
They have a big advantage
over the other team
because they're playing
in their normal rhythm
despite the fact that
they've changed time zones.
So it's more complicated
and more interesting
than just, you know, jet lag,
which is obviously very, very important.
So this rhythm, there's a
ton of information here.
Steven Lockley from Harvard,
he's been around for forever,
has published a ton in this area,
was monumental in developing
the circadian rhythm
and light timing for the
International Space Station.
He has a great app.
I have no affiliation to this,
but it's called Timeshifter,
which helps you set your supplementation
and light and food,
stuff for if you're
traveling internationally.
I've used it for years,
I've paid full price for it.
Lots of stuff there.
But he's done a ton of
research on this stuff,
and it's really compelling.
So Steve has done so much
cool work in this area,
but I'm going to condense it
to just hit a couple of points.
One study I think of in particular was
they went back and looked at
performance in Olympic swimming
from 2004 to 2016,
and they were able to
predict .3% to performance
based simply on circadian timing.
So, again, we're not
talking about who slept more
or who had sleep disorders or anything.
It is simply, can you play
and perform in the right
time for your body?
I think more interesting
is Cheri Mah from Stanford,
who I've mentioned before,
spent I think about three
years working with ESPN.
And what she was able to do is predict
somewhere between the
neighborhood of 70 to 80% accuracy
of who would win NFL games
based simply on the team's time zone.
So this is incredible.
Obviously this is stuff
that people use in,
those in the sports betting
world, behind the scenes a lot.
Part of that information,
if you ever wonder why a betting line
is where it is on some teams,
this is a huge component to that.
It's certainly not the only one,
but it's really cool stuff.
So, again, be able to understand
and enhance your performance.
If sleep extension is out of the question,
if sleep diagnostic is
out of the question,
if sleep quality,
you're trying and it's
not working, whatever,
another way, again, you can get yourself
to huge performance enhancements
is manipulating your timing.
The more you can stay consistent
in performing in your own local space,
whenever you're used to performing,
the better you're going to be.
Let me give you one tangible example
so you have something to lock onto here.
The University of
Washington football team,
my hometown team, candidly,
is going to be dealing
with the unique challenge.
They are right now in the Pac-12,
which means every team they
play is on the West Coast.
They're moving to a division
that is in the Midwest.
So they're going to be
playing Ohio and Pennsylvania
and Iowa and Minnesota
and things like that.
So let's imagine this.
Let's imagine the University of Washington
typically played their
football games, as they do,
either at 4:30 pm or
7:30 pm Washington time.
Okay, great.
So if they played a team at 4:30 at home,
and that team came from
the East Coast or Midwest,
University of Washington has an advantage.
The other team traveled,
and now they're competing
at their normal, local time.
Huge win for the University of Washington.
But another scenario
gets more interesting.
Let's imagine that they're on the road,
and let's imagine they went
to Ohio State, as an example,
and they played that game at
7:30 pm Eastern Time Zone.
Now, this is actually still,
despite the fact that they're on the road,
this is still a huge advantage
for the University of Washington
because 7:30 East Coast time
is still 4:30 West Coast time.
So not only is the
University of Washington
competing on their
normal circadian rhythm,
but Ohio State, in this case,
is competing at a way delayed rhythm.
Typically those teams
are going to be playing
at about noon local time.
So instead of playing at noon local time,
they're now playing at 7:30 local time.
They've shifted their
performance window 7 1/2 hours.
So in this particular case,
despite the fact that
we would be on the road
and we'd have a 3-hour
time zone difference,
there would still be a
slight one to 2% advantage
for the University of Washington.
Third example here would be the opposite.
Let's imagine again,
University of Washington typically plays
at 4:30 pm Seattle time.
And they go to Columbus or Ohio State
and they play a game at
Columbus, or Ohio's normal time,
which is noon Eastern Time, right?
This is now 9:00 in the morning
for the University of Washington.
This is now many, what do we,
almost eight hours earlier than normal.
Would be a massive advantage,
not only because of the time shift change,
the travel, being on the road,
but because of circadian rhythms.
You would probably be
looking at, you know,
maybe a four to five to 6%
advantage just on that fact alone
to the Ohio State team.
So something to really pay attention to.
Those of you that have the opportunity
or ability to manipulate this,
I would encourage you to do so.
But something, again, we
can really pay attention to
when sleep extension or sleep
quality are not on the table
as variables that we can improve.
If you enjoyed this clip,
you can watch the full
episode by clicking here.
[music]